[Music]
welcome to this session on what's new in
server and database a faster data stack
this is number two out of four sessions
on news in the server and data base part
should we get started I think we should
because we have lots of cool stuff to
cover
here let's talk a little bit about
companion tables prior to this
release in uh the way the data model
where we store table extension data has
always been um that we store each table
extension in its own table and then at
runtime we enforce a onetoone
relationship between the base table and
each extension table the primary key for
the base is also the primary key for all
companion tables that's the name we call
these physical
tables now when you when we then fetch
the data from the AL runtime we will
simply join all these EXT extension
tables unless you use partial records
and uh this means that the execution
time because of these joints will grow
um linearly probably with the number of
table
extensions and uh the SQL Server query
Optimizer has a hidden Li limit around
seven or eight joints where it will stop
optimizing and simply use one uh join
algorithm um and that means once you get
past that step you might have suboptimal
plans but there's nothing really you can
do it about it or we can do about it it
the the previous only way to get out of
this join issue uh was to use partial
records this would be a way to prune
either um fields or joints yes and the
reason why we actually had that model
was that it made installation on
installation of extensions very easy
because we could basically just leave
the table behind so because that would
have no effect on the other tables but
we decided that per for performance
reasons we wanted to change this model
exactly so there are some behaviors of
this model um an nway join of one to one
tables is slow um now normally if you
have joints it's very often that you
have a driving table which is big and
some smaller tables which are have low
cardinality which are lookup tables in
this EX in this model the number of rows
in the base and the the things you join
to are the same and that's why this this
is this can never be
fast if you have a customer who has
installed a number of apps and
extensions not really any of these
extensions are to blame for a
performance issue because it's just
built into the model and there's no
really easy way to mitigate this problem
you can't ask a customer to uninstall
function it to get speed it's the only
way we could solve this would be the AL
runtime the platform to do it yeah and
and also we sometimes heard Partners
asking so should I create three
extensions or one extension because it's
logical for me to split it into multiple
but that means it'll be
slower now with the new model I can
reveal that it doesn't really matter
anymore seen from a performance point of
view thanks exactly so we changed the
model the data model for table
extensions and now we simply have the
base table and we have one companion
table that stores the fields for all
table extensions and this minimize the
use of joints because you will at most
have one joint instead of uh n
joints and it severely affects in a good
way the performance of of database
operation
delete operations two to five times
faster insert performance twice as fast
on the measurements we have modify can
be also two times faster and read
performance is definitely where we see
the most impact but be careful when you
measure here because the NST the server
caches data so it can be hard to measure
at least you need to flush all caches
before you do your tests and I think
yens is going to talk a little bit more
about the read performance
improvements so this is uh this is how
the tables look prior and now in in
version 20 uh 22 you see uh here in
version 22 that you have the base table
and then for each of the table
extensions you would have their own
table now in the new schema we simply
have the base table and then we have one
companion table that stores all the
fields from each table EX exension and
you'll also notice that in addition to
only having one table and one join the
database size actually also decreases
quite a bit because there is only one
copy of the primary key there is only
one copy of the row version and then of
course you have the individual Fields
meaning that the overall storage usage
is smaller
correct so what's the expected
performance impact let's look at this
graph on the right
you can see version 22 is the blue line
and the orange line here is version
23 and you can see the read performance
simply scales in the old model almost
linearly with the number of table
extensions whereas it it looks much
flatter here for um for the new model
first of all why do we see this uh this
change here that's because it's of
course fastest well this is because you
see one join so so so there's a little
bit there and then the the increase for
the new model is only for the fields the
extra Fields you read whereas in the old
model you also get that penalty from the
joints yeah and the reason why it takes
longer to read more Fields is that
there'll be fewer rows in each data page
so normally you would have to read more
data Pages just to get the one extension
table when it grows larger yeah then why
this um why don't we see a larger
increase in performance for let's say
modify insert delete anything that is
not read this is typically because on
the database you would see a huge impact
but on on the NST and the AL runtime we
often need to run events and that means
that that most bulk operations will
actually not be in effects um and that's
that's that's the primary reason why we
don't see like a huge benefit here and
that's also why it's really hard to
State how much faster will this be re
does not invoke events unless of course
you have an on after get record trigger
but usually just in normal Al code there
are no events evolved the moment you
have modifications we have events that
very often naturally determine the
performance of insert modify
delete so the your mileage will vary
with this um we I mean you can
have different field number of fields
different sizes of fields triggers you
might have different triggers running
you might have tons of indexes a few
indexes so whether you would get a twice
or 5x or 10x really up to to how your
code is organized and the data that you
have yeah and also remember that if
there is only one extension you won't
see a
difference it doesn't really matter
until there are multiple extensions in
play so what's the record we've seen in
prod for number of table extensions do
you remember 70 80 something 70 70 so if
you are that customer with 70 table
extensions you would go from a 70 way
join to a one way join yes and I hope
you are you're listening out there I
sorry for that customer if it's on one
of the larger tables yeah all right you
might wonder but wait a minute what
about Cloud migration since you're
changing the schema like how can we
migrate from earlier versions using the
cloud migration tool we upgraded that so
all good uh version 23 exposed the
mapping from previous versions We
updated the tool so these as a a data
Factory clows now they know about the
new and old um data models and Cloud
migration is fully supported also from
previous versions as it used to be or as
it should be yes you should be aware for
on premises since we are changing the
data model there is quite a bit of data
writing going on during upgrade so when
you upgrade an un premise installation
you should probably expect that to take
a little longer than for instance the
version 21 to 22 upgrade
yeah but wait what if we are on premises
and we have integrated directly to the
database with data warehousing ETL tools
business intelligence what do we do well
first of all maybe you shouldn't because
it's not supported but that's not really
a good answer because of course if you
have been involved with powerbi or other
um tools it would be natural to pointed
to your database on premises the way to
get uh to get out of this once you are
on a new model is that you can mimic the
old schema with database views so it's
possible to for anyone reading the data
uh they don't know whether they're
reading database views or the the
physical model and there are already
code samples out on GitHub so search for
that um at the time of this recording we
we don't have it on BCT Tech we might
get a version of that on BCT Tech so
let's uh let's see but if not search for
code samples to create database views
and I think that will probably unblock
uh most of these things for
you
so we had a huge marketing Splash on
partial records and and uh set load
Fields like this is the thing that will
solve everything and it did solve some
things but now we've solved it in the
platform for the joints so you might ask
is set load field really needed
anymore you can say that in some cases
it will have much less effect if you
used it to remove the joint statements
then that is actually done now by the
platform unless you remove the one joint
to The one extension table but set load
Fields also limit the fields loaded so
that means there is less data to
transfer there is less data to cache and
you can actually also hit covering
indexes so particularly
for um tight Loops where you need to
process a lot of data it'll still make a
big difference particularly if you can
hit an
index so overall continue using setlo
Fields you don't have to sprinkle it all
over your code base but when you have
performance critical code you want to
control which fields are loaded you want
that part to be as fast as possible
whereas for the generic situation where
you didn't optimize now the platform
helps you speaking of helping we had our
own app teams asking for this and it
might help you as well so if you write
code and you're the owner of the base
table uh it might be that you want to be
able to set the bit the to load all the
base Fields so we now have a new method
that allows you to do that and uh we
know developers are lazy and that's a
good thing that's what we want uh you to
to write as much code with as few
statements as possible so uh so maybe
this uh new method will be for you as
well to lower your maintenance cost on
your on your code and still make it
faster and there is an example here
where on vat entry it's just called
set-based load fields and then setting
the range and then doing a f set and
there it is looping now particularly if
the code inside the loop changes then
before with the set load Fields you
would have to remember to go back and
change which Fields you loaded if you
started accessing a new field inside
your Loop now this one will at least
remove the join um but again if this is
performance critical code and you really
want to optimize then you can use the
set load fields to minimize what is
cached and loaded
yeah and is this an example from the B
app yes so this is actually something
you can search for in in the base app
code and see the actual example how it's
being used yes so if you're in doubt you
don't really know which feels but you
know that this is just my code I'm not
raising events then putting in a
set-based load Fields is a safe way to
go cool so key takeaways from this new
extension schema the main thing here is
there is no really no action on you
right we we just made things faster for
all code maybe the only action is to
stop worrying about whether you should
put in one or three extension that is
true yeah and you would as as Yen said
if you only have one table extension you
won't see a difference if you have two
or more you will definitely see it
mainly on read maybe even on logging
let's see uh we need to measure that um
Cloud migration it's fine on premises
you need some work uh if you if you
access SQL tables
directly yes now as part of this we also
realized
that if you leave data behind then it
now has a performance impact because
before as I mentioned it would just sit
in a separate table nobody would really
care about that table except if you're
looking for database storage but now it
is part of the extension tables row so
if you've uninstalled an extension but
did not delete the um actual data then
it uses database capacity and it also
makes joining with this extension table
slightly slower so we've added the
ability to remove it if you had
forgotten to Mark the delete extension
data when you uninstalled your extension
it is placed in the installed extensions
now that can actually be a little
sarcastic because you're deleting stuff
from the not installed extensions from
the installed extensions but it was
still the most natural place for us to
put it where you can delete the ofen
extensions data and then it'll show you
which extensions still have Remnant in
the database and you can then decide to
delete it and that way it gets removed
this also means that after you've done
this step if you reinstall the extension
then you won't have the data and that
was actually how you have to do it
before if you had forgotten to delete it
you needed to reinstall delete and then
uninstall again but that is no longer
needed
cool a lot about uh data Reading Writing
another part of data is
locking and uh we actually also have
some cool new stuff going on
here yes we have enable the ability to
change the Locking model to minimize or
at least to automatically take fewer
logs in Al and this is a thing that
benefits all usage scenarios web
services Integrations background jobs
and interactive
sessions um and of course there are two
ways that you can improve the Locking
situation you can lock less or you can
just make your code faster so the first
part we just talked about here will
actually help unlocking because you hold
the locks for shorter if the code is
faster but what do we talk about when we
talk about the new locking model well
before and this may not be obvious to
everyone we had
the um approach that the moment we
entered into a right transaction then we
would start taking logs on any table
that was modified so in this case here
first it'll do read on committed then
you do an insert into that table and
then when you read from that same table
type in this case the currency table
then that would be read with an update
lock can I say something here of course
you because I think the the gotcha here
is when I saw this code sample I was
like what so the the lock the update
lock is actually taken on a different
record uh instance you can see c 2 is is
uh is is a new instance of that so why
would you take a lock well this is
because the old Behavior was that
whenever you do a change on a table then
all uh new instances on the same table
in the same session will inherit the
lock and I think that was a gotcha for
many yes it definitely was and there are
some deeper lying reasons for that for
instance when you pass a record from one
function to another if you don't pass it
by bar you get a new record so now if
you did something down there you
actually had a new record so there are
some reasons why it was like this um and
we've had to do some tricks in order to
keep the old Behavior but with the new
locking enable then after modifying and
entering the after the insert statement
here then further reads on other um
record instances pointing to the same
table will now be done with a read
committed
so for a given record type as long as
you have not entered into a right
transaction then all reads have the read
uncommitted hint applied and then when
the data has been written or some data
has been written to the record type in
the current transaction then further
reads will have the read committed hint
applied now you can still do lock table
lock table has not changed that is your
way to say well I still want this
automatic application of update lock so
if lock table has been called and
further reads will have the update lock
hint applied and this is important
because when you look at the Bas app
code right now in version
23 um there will still be a lot of lock
table statements sprinkled over all over
that code but we're changing that with
the app teams in the in the next
releases so that we will try to make the
Bas app much more concurrent friendly
and less locking and you should do the
same for your code if you have of course
you have because before this you
couldn't otherwise right you would you
would have lock table sprinkled over
your code as well and you need to look
at these critically and see do I really
need to do exclusive locks with lock
table or can we maybe do better and and
do the the new logging re yeah you you
talked about the different record
instances and you can control the
Locking behavior on an instance level by
using the read isolation property which
is one way to avoid calling lock table
you can basically opt out saying I want
to read this with an update lock but I
don't really want it to just to do a
lock table
correct and here is sort of a summary of
the before and after
situation um we talked about the update
lock versus recommitted and basically
the effect is now that you'll only
acquire shared lck when reading other
data from that table and that means that
you can
read other data from that table and
other session can do the same now the
record that you're actually modifying
will basically be just as L as before
but sort of the inadvertent locking of
other records is now not happening when
you enable this new locking
schema so when we designed this and this
actually took two releases so there when
you set the isolation level um that was
in the wave One release we wanted to put
that in for before we went to this and
we were kind of oh dear are we are we
breaking everything we don't know we
don't think we are but just to be
cautious yes so we have added this as a
feature management switch so you can
enable it uh and it should be noticed of
course things will still work
functionally there is no change you
still have transactional consistency of
course but you might get the another
user has modified this in case you have
certain code paths we have not seen
issues with this in our base app but we
cannot rule out we can think of examples
where you could get in
to a different Behavior where you would
see this that another user has modified
the record and this is part of so
concurrency testing is one of the most
difficult ways to test code right that's
why I put in yens didn't know that but
he can you can see this bcpt question
mark in there because there is actually
a tool that can help you do concurrency
tests and and flesh out locking issues
so one tip here is that enable this in
sandboxes and make some scenarios in in
this business Central performance
toolkit where you are able to do
concurrency tests and that might be a
good way to see whether your code is
actually taking fewer locks or if it's
act could be that it's
taking other locks or maybe having more
Deadlocks but you would be able to to
detect it using this bcpt tool correct
and the way we're going to roll this out
is the that in this release then
upgraded tenants can opt in via the
through the feature management page as
we showed before for new tenants this is
automatically enabled but you can flip
this back and forth at at will um so
that but it is done for all users so you
don't have Kenny running with One
locking scheme and Yen's running with
another one um but it is something that
can be moved back and forth for testing
so you can also compare with and without
just one gutcher here what yens was
saying with the all users you actually
need a restart of the environment yes
for this for this switch to take effect
so just be aware of that and that's in
order to not mix and match yes um these
from the from the next version we will
enable this by default but you can still
disable it and then from version
25 then the new locking will will be the
way we do
locking now there are a few other
performance improvements in the data sty
that are worth mentioning you might have
seen that autoincrement Fields made very
wide tables slow that has been optimized
there was an inefficient parameter
generation algorithm that made it worse
and worse and if you had 100 Fields Auto
increment would actually start taking
seconds um that has been fixed and it's
a lot faster now and we've also
optimized the SQL queries we generate
from set range um so that SQL has a
better chance of picking an optimal
index there are also a few changes that
are upcoming in 2024 release way one the
server settings for Force order and loop
joints will be removed so that you don't
have the opportunity to run run that in
the old way this is how we've been
running for years in the
service um and also for on premises you
might run with the ability to write to
the app database we will remove that um
possibility from the next
release cool so Goos the most important
thing is test the new locking scheme try
to run some bcpt tests and check for
errors has check for logging or
Deadlocks if you you maybe you don't
know but maybe go and find find out if
you have deleted um or often data that
can be delet deleted you can save on
storage you can save on performance and
uh the third thing is if you write to
the appdb stop in six months this will
stop working so um this is um yeah we
we're getting rid of the appdb as a
concept so so that's these changes uh
and this is one of the changes in
that what else should you watch of
course if you're watching this you also
have an interest probably in the
language so the developer tools watch
new and Al is uh definitely a session
worth watching and then specifically in
this serious uh the session the fourth
session in the watchs new and server and
database is about reporting but under
the hood we have some cool new things to
talk about with cies and maybe that
Cliffhanger we should just leave it here
and then just refer to the business
Central
resources take the discussions on Yammer
join the conversations on X um submit
your ideas to BC ideas Etc and um hope
that we will get some good feedback on
this and other things and looking
forward to hearing from
you thank you thank
you